Well, this is an exciting moment because this is the start of your next masterpiece.
As in this lesson, we'll be starting to develop our next game.
And I hate to say it, but this one will put all your past projects to shame.
So let's do this.
And I think by now you know the drill.
First things first, let's start by creating our new projects.
And just like all the other tabs, we can do this simply by clicking this button here.
Okay, now before we do anything, if you look to the top here, you can see our project is just called
untitled, which is a bit uninspired.
So the first thing we can do is rename this to Arcade Ski Adventure or whatever you like.
And one more thing.
You can delete this default cat sprite as we definitely don't need it in this project.
So no skiing for the cat.
Now, with that out of the way, before we import any sprites or do anything, we need to get a high
level overview of our game to understand what it is, what it does, and then what steps we can take
to achieve this.
Because remember, it's important to break down a big problem into achievable steps.
And we discussed how we can follow a three step workflow when making games, which were setting up the
basic structure of the game, then developing the gameplay mechanics and finally polishing the game.
Now those three steps are cool and all, but while this method works great for smaller games, for more
ambitious projects, we need a more detailed plan of action.
So let me introduce you to the expanded five step process tailor made for larger games, and following
this guide will help you a lot with the exciting games, apps, and animations you will produce in the
future.
Stage one.
Ideas and design.
At this stage, it's all about ideas.
Imagine it as sketching the blueprint for our game.
What's the storyline?
What kind of characters are we looking at?
What's the central theme?
By the end of this phase, we'll have a comprehensive game design idea that outlines everything about
our game.
Stage two setting up the Foundation.
Think of this as laying the bricks and mortar for our game, just like before.
Here we'll be importing all the sprites you need and then laying them out so you have a better idea
of how it will all work.
Stage three, developing core gameplay mechanics.
Here the game starts to show signs of life.
This is where the real action begins coding, player movements, setting game logic, designing levels
and everything that makes our game well, a game.
Stage four Enhancement and expansion.
Now that we have a playable game, it's time to add layers to it.
Maybe a new level, or a challenging enemy, or even a surprise power up.
This stage is all about adding features and upgrading our game.
So when you get to stage four, you need to go back to stage one.
So let's say we want a new enemy in our game here you would have to go back to the design stage, then
to importing it, then to developing its mechanics if you get the idea.
And then finally stage five polishing and finalization.
This is the final touch.
We'll refine the graphics, introduce sound effects, fine tune the user interface, and rigorously
test our game to iron out any bugs and enhance the overall user experience.
So by following this structured five step process, we'll ensure that our game development journey is
organized, efficient, and most importantly, enjoyable.
And remember, every big game starts with just a simple idea.
With careful planning and step by step execution, there's really no limit to what we can achieve.
But with all that out the way, let's get going with step one.
And this should be quick enough because we kind of already know what we want for our game.
So basically we want something not too different from our last game.
And here we're going to have these obstacles that come towards us that we need to dodge.
And this again will give the player the illusion of motion.
But this time it will look like they are skiing down a mountain, through a forest.
And here we want the trees to fade into view and our player to have a nice turning effect.
We also want our player to have snow pixels that follow them, which should look like ski marks you
would see in normal snow.
And that's basically it for the first part of our game.
Then we add new things like a start screen, a restart button, and other exciting stuff that we can
revisit these first steps, but get ready because in the next lesson we will be incorporating all our
sprites.